this is the third lecture and
it is about multi-threaded programming
as always here you have the reading
instructions it is chapter 2.2 and
10.3.3 but there are concepts there that
we will discuss in future lectures too
and as always you also have the extra facultative
reading if you want from the other book
the objectives for this lecture are to
introduce the notion of a thread it's a
fundamental concept in operating systems we also
discuss APIs for example for the pthreads library
we will look at several strategies that provide
implicit threading and also discuss some of the
issues and challenges related to multi-threaded
programming but let's start with introducing a bit
threads and actually what I'm going
to do is to go back to a slide I
show you in the processes lecture
so we had these two sentences
we run several programs at the same time and
one CPU can only run one program at the time
and I mentioned before that these two
sentences are not really correct meaning
they're not completely wrong but if you want to be
precise especially in the context of this course
you probably want to say that we feel several
programs run at the same time you remember we
have discussed context switches so the fact
that the operating system together with the
hardware is continuously switching the process
it runs so it gives you this feeling of things
running at the same time while
in practice only one at the time is running
but what we will see today is that indeed it
is possible to have multiple processes that are
actually running at the same time so if you
freeze time and you look inside your computer
your hardware your CPU you might find that there
are multiple processes running at the same time
so if you actually freeze time and
you look inside your hardware your
CPU you can find that two instructions from
different processes or even from the same
process we will see why both things can happen
could be potentially be executed physically at
the same time okay so the right way to put it
is that each CPU core can only run one program
at a time but it's the core not the entire CPU
this is what we will discuss in this lecture
and you remember I show you this I said this
is the main activity done by the brain of the
computer the CPU it's a simplified version
there is also the checking for interrupts
is not there so when you have a multi-core
CPU what happens is that inside each core
you have one such brain that can be fetching
the next instruction and then running
that instruction and this can happen in
parallel at the same time you can have this
execute instruction with different instructions
being executed physically at the same time